Hi, I am Jennifer Boss and welcome to
five Questions on Virtual Coaching.
I'm Mi Louise Heeder and I'm on
faculty at Vanderbilt University
and work with DTL on coaching.
So, um, what are the key considerations
for coaches and coaches to keep in
mind for effective virtual coaching?
One of the things I think is that we
have to remember that you still have
to do coaching the way it was designed.
And so that means that
relationships are important.
That means that you have to have a plan.
That means that you have to have a way
to observe that you have a good way
to do reflection and feedback, but it
also means you have to be flexible,
especially in this virtual world.
And so what does that mean to.
flexible when it comes to coaching?
Well, I think that means that we have
to be really intentional about picking
effective practices to focus on that
are relevant to the virtual setting.
So if a home visitor's working with a
parent and that child is at home alone,
I mean at home without other kids around,
it probably doesn't make sense to work on
teaching friendship skills, but it might.
Be important to work on structuring
routines and helping children
learn about their daily routines.
So we gotta really think about
effective practices that are relevant.
Um, I think we have to adjust our goals.
I think we have to make sure
that the goals that we're.
choosing are things that the
coach or the teacher or the
home visitor wants to work on.
And I think more than ever in the virtual
setting that we really need to think about
how are people gonna feel successful?
Because I think right now it's
hard to feel really successful.
And so we might wanna pick goals,
um, that are gonna help people.
, it feels successful more quickly.
And then the last thing I wanna just
mention is that I think we have to
be transparent in coaching virtually
about things that might be stressful
to teachers or home visitors.
So if we're gonna be videotaping,
that could be stressful, right?
So let's just be transparent
about why we're videotaping.
We're gonna video tape.
So that the coach or the home visitor
or the teacher can review the video
and we're not gonna be videotaping to
give that video to some supervisor.
So I think if we're just transparent
about it, about what we're gonna
do with the video, that we can
help people feel more comfortable.
So, , how do coaches build, maintain,
and strengthen relationships
with coachee in a virtual space?
That seems like the kind of million
dollar question, I think, in a lot of
ways, and I think that there's lots
of strategies we can use that are
not really all that different than
what we would do in a live space.
Um, but I think some things
might become more important.
So I think we wanna be sure that in
our, that in our coaching sessions,
that we're building in time for casual
conversation that we're checking in
with the teacher or the home visitor,
whoever we're coaching about things
that we know are important to them.
So we might be checking in with
them about their new puppy dog, or
we might be checking in with them
about how their kids are doing, or.
, but we're saving some time in giving
some time to just checking in with them.
I think we wanna celebrate, we wanna
celebrate little wins because little
wins virtually might feel like big wins.
And that might be coaching
successes, it might be, um, personal
successes, but we wanna be sure we're
celebrating, um, those successes.
I think we wanna give coaches.
time to get used to the technology.
And so I think that the whole
technology thing may feel really
uncomfortable to some coaches.
Um, and I think we have to kind of
build in opportunities for people to
practice the technology without the
pressure of re reflection and feedback.
So we probably don't wanna
have the first time we.
Are gonna watch a video
be about coaching, right?
So maybe we just have a visit
where we say, we're gonna figure
out how to upload videos here.
I'm gonna upload a video of
myself and let's look at it.
And then what if, what if you
brought a video of your, your child
or something and let's upload it.
And let's just talk about the process
up of uploading and watching videos.
So what should coaches be observing?
when they're working with teachers
or home visitors who are supporting
virtual learning at home.
And what are some of the
strategies that they can use,
uh, during virtual observations?
I think we have to maybe reframe a little
bit what we think about observations
and what can count as an observ.
Observation.
I think the first thing that we wanna
always remember is that whatever
we're doing related to observation
is based on the action plan.
And that, again, just
creates this safe space.
But I think we can think outside
the box of what it means to observe.
So it might mean we observe a teacher
doing a lesson with a group of kids.
Vir on their virtual platform.
Or it might mean that we observe
a home visitor doing a home visit
during, on the virtual platform.
But it might also mean that we're not
necessarily looking at the teacher, but
we're saying to the teacher, we're gonna,
we're gonna watch to see if children are
engaged and we're gonna kind of prompt
you for the kids who aren't engaged, cuz
it's too hard to be doing this virtual
learning and looking at a picture.
10 kids and figuring out
what kids are engaged.
So we can take a little bit of
pressure off by saying, we're gonna
look at the children, or we're gonna
look at the family, versus looking
at the teacher or the home visitor.
So what are some strategies coaches
can use for providing constructive
feedback to teachers and home visitors
during virtual coaching sessions?
One is that I would say we
should be really intentional
about grounding our feedback in
what we hear the coachee saying.
So we might think a session went
really well, and when we asked the
coachee, the home visitor, , they might
say, I thought that was a disaster.
So how do we ground our feedback
and our reflection in that, in the
perception of the coachee versus kind
of putting our own feelings on that?
I think one way to make help people
feel more comfortable is to focus our
feedback on the children or on the
families, meaning whoever the coachee.
So if the home visitors working with
the family or that teachers working with
kids that we're focusing on the family
and children and how they're responding
and how they're understanding what
goes on, that takes a little bit of.
Pressure off the the teacher or the home
visitor and it says, okay, so this child
looked like they weren't so engaged.
What could we do to support that child?
Feels a little less pressure.
I think we wanna avoid any kind of
feedback about technology cuz we're
all struggling with technology and we
just need to be helpful in that way.
Um, I really want people to be
sensitive to the limitations imposed
on teachers and home visitors and be
sure we're not giving them feedback
about things they can't control.
I think there's a couple of strategies
we can use that might not initially sound
like feedback, but served to be feedback.
I think share, asking teachers,
asking home visitors if you can share
their successes with other teachers
in-home visitors is a way of saying
what you're doing is really great.
And I think given this context
of all of us kind of learning as
we go, saying to you a coachee.
You know, I might wanna ask some of my
other coaches how they're handling that,
how their teachers are handling that, or
how their home visitors are handling that.
And that just again, says we're all
learning that we're all trying to
get better at doing this and that
none of us have all the answers.
what are some words of encouragement
that you want to share with coaches?
Um, with teaching staff and home
visitors and parents who are all
working together in this virtual space.
People have been doing research on
virtual coaching for a long time,
but people haven't been doing.
re research on virtual coaching to
coach people to teach virtually, right.
And so what that makes me think
is that we're just all learning.
We're all learning, we're
all gonna make mistakes.
I think we have to assume good
intentions in the work that we're doing.
I think we have to assume that we're
all struggling, that we're all,
um, trying to do the best we can,
that we're all trying to juggle.
Kids and animals and jobs and houses and
partners and all of those kind of things.
And that we just have to assume
everybody's doing the best they
can under these situations.
And then I just wanna close by saying
that, you know, I think we're tempted.
To want to be fancy during this
time, to think about fancy ways to
have backgrounds behind us or having
a Bitmoji classroom or whatever.
But the people we're supporting
don't care about Fancy.
They want connections
and they want support.
And I think we know how
to make connections.
We know how to support
people and fancy is.
But being connected, being
supportive, even in the absence
of fancy, of fancy backgrounds,
is gonna make us more successful.